Individually catalogued manuscripts, 1591-2005 Various call numbers
Lilly Library
- Odelette guerrière, 1870
  Lilly Library copy is a unique volume, illustrated with 5 original watercolors by French artist/illustrator Albert Bligny (1849-1908). The illustrations are interspersed throughout the text and are signed "A. Bligny." The volume was bound by Marius Michel in full red morroco, gilt decorations, green silk and marbled endpapers, with original printed wrappers bound in. Bookseller's printed slip, "With compliments, Quevedo Tobias Rodgers, Justine Budenz ...," tipped in at front.
- Ich bin dieser Streifen - Samuel Beckett, 2008
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8083661
  A unique artist's book by Thomas Offhaus, with his original watercolor illustrations coupled with letterpress text. Bound in rust-colored illustrated boards, edges untrimmed, with black leather shelfback.
- Worstward Ho - Samuel Beckett, 2008
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8071514
  A unique artist's book, with cursive holograph text and original acrylic paintings by Zylla on facing pages. Zylla pairs his large picturesque panels with selections from Samuel Beckett's "Worstward Ho." According to Beckett scholar, Dirk Van Hulle: "It is an attempt to reach the worst possible condition, which proves to be an asymptotic journey: like the infinitesimal attempt to reach 'nothing' with words, the worst cannot be attained with words. For as Shakespeare already wrote in King Lear: 'And worse may I be yet; the worst is not, So long as we can say This is the worst' (IV.1.27-28). Beckett copied this sentence in his 'Sottisier' notebook (RUL MS 2901) while or shortly before he was writing Worstward Ho" (The Literary Encyclopedia website, 03/12/09).
- Bon bon il est un pays Gut gut es gibt ein Land - Samuel Beckett, 2009
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9531234
  A unique artist's book on double leaves with cursive holograph text and original artwork by Angela Hampel; author's name, title and artist's name are from the accompanying green printed slipcase (German translation of poem is printed in white on the front of the slipcase). Signed by the artist and dated, 2009, on p. [4] of wrappers. Accompanied by one grey sheet with the German translation by Elmar Tophoven of a Samuel Beckett poem, Bon bon il est un pays, originally published in the collection Six poèmes (1947-1949) printed in white; signed in typescript: "Samuel Beckett, uübersetzt von Elmar Tophoven." Both items are housed in a green cloth clamshell case.
- Le dépeupleur - Samuel Beckett, 2009
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9531456
  A unique artist's book, with cursive holograph text and original artwork by Klaus Zylla on facing pages. Zylla pairs his large picturesque panels with selections from Samuel Beckett's "Le dépeupleur."
- Flötentöne (Mirlitonnades) - Samuel Beckett, 2006
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9531458
  A unique artist's book with cursive holograph text and original artwork by Antje Wichtrey. Signed and dated by the artist on the back pastedown: "Granada/Gotha 2006."
- Le moine de M.G. Lewis raconté par Antonin Artaud, ca. 1931
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8114716
  Holograph manuscript, signed at end, undated. Leaves numbered 1-5 with an additional "page 3 bis à inserer." A review discussing Artaud's adaptation of a French translation of M. G. Lewis's Gothic novel, The monk (Paris: Denoël et Steele, 1931). Cocteau comments that translation is done to overcome crises of sterilty.
- Letters, photographs, and ephemera related to Ionesco, 1969-2001
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8431514
  Collection includes two letters, five black and white photographs, and a newspaper clipping of a book review. Both letters are typed and signed by Ionesco to Rosette Lamont, one dated May 20, 1969, the other dated Jan. 11, 1980. The five black and white photographs (four of which are by Beverly Pabst) each feature Ionesco: [1] Ionesco sitting on a chair in a patch of lawn surrounded by tall trees; marked in pencil on the verso: "Eugène Ionesco a Cerisy-la-Selle/l'ete 1978" and inscribed by Pabst for Rosette [Lamont]; [2] a close-up of Ionesco reading a newspaper, with Pabst's stamp on the verso; [3] Ionesco smiling and holding a microphone on a stage, with Pabst's stamp on the verso; and, [4] Ionesco pensively holding a microphone on stage, with Pabst's stamp on the verso; marked in red China crayon, "Return to J. Harris," and a post-it asking, "do we have consent?" and, in another hand, "Yes!"; and, [5] Ionesco with Rosette Lamont, with a mss. note on verso: "June, 2001. To Rosette, Photo found when cleaning out my mother's house. Love, Penny." The newspaper clipping from The New York Times Book Review, March 23, 1975, includes a review of Story Number 4, the English edition of Ionesco's Conte numéro 4.
- Italo Calvino letter, [197-?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8264422
  This undated typed letter, signed, with several penned corrections, contains a statement on the role and purpose of a translator. In the letter, Calvino praises the "Translation Center at Columbia and its magazine" with its educational mission to study and improve the "difficult art of translating." Written on personal stationery, with the author's name printed in light grey italics: "Italo Calvino."
- Short collection of verse - de Macedo and du Bocage, ca. 1802
  Gift: 2013
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/16814479
  Selection of manuscript poems by late 18th-century and early 19th-century Portuguese poets, all copied on laid paper in the same hand. Opens with "Satyra: Que [Ser?] Jose Agostinho de Macedo a Manoel Maria de Barbosa du Bocage"--page 27. Followed by "Resposta de Manoel Maria de Barbosa du Bocage. Á Satyraque lhe [Ser?] Jose Agostinho de Macedo. 1802" (page 34). Final section composed of "Poesias de Manoel Maria Barbosa du Bocage" and "Verdades duras" (ages 46 and 52). Only date to appear in the text is 1802. Verso of penultimate leaf signed in purple by Antonio Antunes d'Almeida, possibly the owner and copyist.
- John Whaley printed receipt with signature, 1745
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8230864
  A printed receipt of purchase for a copy of A Collection of original poems and translations, by John Whaley (see Foxon, p. 888), with the receipt number, the buyer's information and Whaley's signature in ink. The work was "printed for the author" in 1745 and sold by subscription. The receipt is numbered 99 and was given to "Mr. West" in exchange for five shillings "being the full payment for a copy of A Collection of Poems, by Mr. John Whaley, which I promise to deliver in Sheets, as soon as printed." The "Mr. West" noted on the receipt is James West (1703-1772), the politician and noted bookcollector.
- The Indian judge: a reminiscence of Poona, 1885
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11653038
  Autograph manuscript of Arnold's poem The Indian judge. The poem is in pencil and contains a few small corrections in Arnold's hand.
- Richard Doddridge Blackmore letter, 1895
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8264435
  A holograph note, signed, by R.D. Blackmore to an unidentified female correspondent regarding the translation of "Erema" or "Springhaven" into French. The note reads: "Dear Madam, I have not head that either 'Erema' or 'Springhaven' has been translated into French; but once or twice I have discovered long afterwards that 'French leave' had been taken. Believe me faithfully yours, R.D. Blackmore ..." With a newspaper cutout printed portrait of Blackmore affixed to top of letter.
- French translation of Sonnets from the Portuguese, ca. 1942-1943
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8184414
  Two items ([5] loose leaves and 1 notebook): (1) Propos litteraries de la traduction des poèmes: five loose leaves of Maurois' holograph notes for his introduction to Browning's Sonnets from the Portuguese (Brentanos, 1944) and his thoughts on translating poetry in general. In the introduction, he reflects: To translate a poem is difficult; to translate it into verse is almost impossible. (2) Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Sonnets traduits du portugais, Traduction franc̦aise de André Maurois: Maurois' holograph notebook of his French translation of Browning's Sonnets from the Portuguese and his introduction (in French) to the 1944 Brentanos' published edition (see Lilly PR4189 .A1 1944). There are a few penciled corrections to the sonnets (appearing to be "final" drafts of his translations), whereas the introduction ([7] leaves at end) bears numerous corrections and changes. Laid in the notebook are two loose printed leaves (18 x 13 cm.) of page proofs(?) (p. 79-80, 95-96, which include the French translations of sonnets XIX-XX and XXVII-XXVIII).
- Ode to Napoleon Buonaparte, 1927
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9383913
  Illuminated manuscript on vellum
- Verses - W. H. Dowding, 1859-1918
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8068277
  William Harris Dowding, newspaper poet, of Bristol, England. His collected verse was published in To freedom's lover and other pieces by William Harris Dowding; selected after sixty years of verse-making. Bristol: J.W. Arrowsmith; London: Simpkin, Marshall, Hamilton, Kent & Co., 1917.
- Alexander Dyce letter, 3 Jan. 1836
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767871
  Holograph letter from Alexander Dyce to Sir Samuel Egerton Brydges, January 3, 1836, London. Dyce discusses publishing and the literary scene in London. He describes his encounters with and impressions of William Wordsworth and Robert Southey, and he mentions the habits and forthcoming publications of several individuals, including John Mitford, Thomas Frognall Dibdin, Dawson Turner, and John Campbell (1766-1840). See vertical file for transcription.
- John Quinn letter, 17 July 1909
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981831
  Typed letter (1 sheet ([1] p.)) signed, from John Quinn to Adrian H. Joline regarding John M. Synge's book "Poems and Translations." Quinn mentions John M. Synge's recent death in March 1909.
- Memories a Neo-Georgian - Edgar Jepson, [1936?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9628332
  Author's first draft and corrected galleys of Memories of an Edwardian and neo-Georgian, published by Martin Secker in 1937 and republished the following year as Memories of an Edwardian. A mixture of holograph and typescript leaves, extensively revised and corrected by the author, many leaves with manuscript or typed sections pasted on. An important and entertaining account of four decades of bohemian literary life, with recollections of Dowson, Machen, Frank Harris, Richard Middleton, Ford, T.S. Eliot, Pound, and many others. The textual differences between the manuscript and the published book become extensive from chapter 17 onwards. At chapter 20, the manuscript ends at what is the first paragraph of p. 263 of the published book, which carries on for a further 11 pages, including a closing chapter. The final sentence of the manuscript contains his last words on D.H. Lawrence: "Above all it should not be forgotten that he possessed to a pre-eminent degree the quality most necessary to a great literary success in England, the power of boring the humanist to tears."
- Alan Kennington scrapbook, [1939-1956]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9627309
  A collection of newspaper clippings from various press-cutting services and a scrapbook containing mounted publishing and theater ephemera, ranging in date from 1939 to 1956, assembled by British playwright and novelist Alan Kennington. The scrapbook includes items relating to Kennington's career including letters, telegrams, documents, reviews, newspaper and magazine clippings, and book jacket samples. There are letters from "The Playwrights' Club," agents, film companies, and the BBC. Clippings are pasted on pages 1-114 of the blank scrapbook (pages have printed numbers). Pages 115-200 are blank.
- Loaves and fishes: a comedy in four acts: playscript, 1911?
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8235585
  Cover title. Annotated typescript, with the manuscript notes and ownership label of Peter Cotes. The cast of Cote's 1951 production of Loaves and fishes, 27 March 1951 (see Who's Who in the Theatre: A Biographical Record of the Contemporary Stage 1952), are written in ms. on leaf [1]. Inscribed and signed by producer Peter Cotes: "This was my script for the first [?] of Maugham's very last play, produced in 1911 and revived by me in 1950, Peter Cotes." In original brown wrappers, typed title on front cover.
- Alan Sillitoe letters, 1959-1960
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981731
  Two holograph letters (3 sheets ([6] p.)) signed, from Alan Sillitoe to calligrapher John C. Tarr and wife, Dorothy. Letters describe progress with his writing, describing finishing Loneliness of the long distance runner, his winning the Authors' Club First Novel Award in 1958 for Saturday night and Sunday morning and winning the Hawthornden Prize in 1960 for Loneliness of the Long Distance Runner.
- Carmela Moya typescript poems, 1980
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11981390
  Collection conists cheifly of poems in typescript and manuscript. Poems consist of 38 sheets of selected poems. Most of the poems are in typescript, others photocopied, with many pages signed, for possible book publication. One sheet with some biographical information about Moya written by David Gascoyne. Also includes one envelope where poems were originally held and sent to David Gascoyne in Colchester, England.
- William Dean Howells letter, 13 Nov. 1906
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8264420
  A holograph letter, signed, from W.D. Howells to Mr. Garrison, of the Boston Houghton, Mufflin, & Co., 13 Nov. 1906, with instructions to accept the "New York concerns offer for Silas Lapham." Written on Hotel Regent (New York City) letterhead, with the dated (14 Nov. 1906) ink stamp of the Houghton, Mifflin office. Included also is a fragment of another letter with Howells' signature and an autographed calling card belonging to Howells.
- William A. Bixler's James Whitcomb Riley collection, 1913-1949
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8431505
  Collection consists of 17 items: 1. Two souvenir "James Whitcomb Riley Birthplace, Greenfiled, Indiana" pinback buttons -- 2. William A. Bixler's copy of The James Whitcomb Riley reader (edited by Charity Dye, Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill, c1915) -- 3. Advertisement sheet (1 folded leaf ([4] p.)) and a photocopy of "A Dream That Came True," with instructions on how to order "a painting made to order of the Ol' Swimming Hole" by Bixler -- 4. Newsclipping (no date) "Riley, the Hoosier Poet, Pleased with Oil Painting of the 'Old Swimming Hole," Praises Artist Wm. A. Bixler" -- 5. Newsclipping from the Indiana Sunday Star (Feb. 2. 1913), "Painter Artist Born in Sod House Wins Riley's Favor" -- 6. Newsclipping from the Sunday Star (Indiana Star) (July 13, 1941), "Riley Day Observed at Tailholt Made Famous in His Poems" -- 7. Advertisement sheet for Bixler's "Autumn Leaves" book -- 8. Newsclipping from The News-Herald (Dec. 22, 1941), "Famous Painting is Copied in Franklin" -- 9. Two copies (different variants) of the booklet, "From the Birthplace of James Whitcomb Riley," issued by the Greenfield Art Association ([12] p.: ill.; 21 cm.) -- 10. Newsclipping (no date, Sun. Oct. 20), "Historic Home Plans Day with Riley"-- 11. Newsclipping from the Milwaukee, Wis., Journal Green Sheet (May 15, 1941), "Author-Singer Painted the Same Picture 5,000 Times" -- 12. One sheet (1 sheet ([1] p.): ill.; 23 cm.) of The Old-Fashioned Dinner Bell (poem) by Bixler -- 13. One folded sheet (39 cm.), "Riley Program Broadcast Here" -- 14. One booklet ([8] p.: ill.; 14 cm.) James Whitcomb Riley Centennial, 1849-1949, with the address label of Wm. A. Bixler on back cover.
- James Whitcomb Riley's walking stick, Between 1870 and 1916
  Gift: 2001
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9534719
  Wooden walking stick (80 cm. in length) with leaf carvings at the top once belonging to Indiana author James Whitcomb Riley.
- Walt Whitman in St. Louis literature, politics, and the prairie states, 1879-1900
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10027190
  See vertical file for bookseller's description. Includes several items (two manuscript notes and one printed newspaper clipping) pasted to a leaf of brown wrapping paper (43 x 18 cm.) by Whitman; there are numerous holograph revisions and editorial corrections for the accompanying newspaper clipping (39 x 7 cm.) in Whitman's hand. Affixed to the top of the brown paper is a holograph introduction to the article, signed in the third person three times by Whitman (1 sheet ([2] p.); 17 x 15 cm.). Affixed to the bottom of the brown paper is a holograph note (1 sheet ([1] p.); 8 x 18 cm.) signed by R[obert] U[underwood] Johnson, dated "New York, March 31, 1900," explaining the circumstances under which Whitman sent his introduction and revisions to him.
- James Agee letter, October 1932
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981835
  Author, journalist, poet, screenwriter, and film critic James Agee (1909-1956) was born in Knoxville, Tennessee. After his father's death, he was educated at Saint Andrew's school for mountain boys, run by Episcopalian monks affiliated with the Order of the Holy Cross, where he met and began his friendship with Father James Harold Flye. He attended Phillip Exeter Academy, where he was the editor of the Monthly, and was accepted to Harvard University's class of 1932. At Harvard he was the editor-in-chief of the Harvard Advocate. On his graduation he became a journalist for Fortune Magazine. He also wrote for Time Magazine, and worked for The Nation as a film critic. His works include Let Us Now Praise Famous Men (1941) and the posthumous A Death in the Family (1955), in addition to his screenplays for African Queen (1951) and The Night of the Hunter (1955).
- Materials related to Kay Boyle, 1965-1983
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11179109
  Collection consists of various materials and correspondence by and about Kay Boyle. Collection includes an invitation to Peggy Sarasohn from Kay Boyle, along with a transcript of Sarasohn's testimony before the House Committee on Un-American Activities; a poem, "Songs for the beginnings," by Steve White, including a ms. note; a typed copy of "A statement for El Greco and William Carlos Williams," by Kay Boyle.
- Light Up the Sky - playscript, [1948?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/81783033
  Annotated mimeographed playscript. The stage manager's personal annotated copy, with drawings of the stage set, as well as notes and corrections throughout; accompanied by a loose leaf ([1] p.) with the names of the cast members and their addresses (several names and addresses are added at the bottom of the typescript list in manuscript). According to the Internet Broadway Database, Light up the sky opened on Nov. 18, 1948 and closed on May 21, 1949; the general stage manager was Don Hershey and the stage manager was Terence Little. It is not clear from the script which individual made the notes, etc.
- Trees - Joyce Kilmer, [between 1922 and 1938?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8080720
  Original postage stamp collage. The text of Kilmer's poem is hand lettered, bordered by a scene made from pieces of postage stamps, details added in water-color, probably by Dorothy C. Alyea. The stamps clipped for the collage include a 1 cent B. Franklin, first issued in 1922-1923; a 1/2 cent Nathan Hale, first issued in 1925; a 1 1/2 cent Harding, first issued in 1925; a Special Delivery stamp, first issued in 1925; and a 1 cent George Washington, first issued in 1938.
- Michael McClure letter, [1964?]
  Purchase: 2003
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8649483
  One undated holograph letter signed, written to Bob Wilson of The Phoenix Book Shop, New York, on an illustrated folded card (13 x 9 cm. which opens to 18 x 13 cm.). Printed in capital letters on the cover of the card is: FUCK DEATH, with an illustration of a horse's head surrounded by a horseshoe. According to McClure's website (http://www.mcclure-manzarek.com/mmbiblio.html) this card was printed in "San Francisco: Privately Published, 1959 ... It does not bear Michael McClure's name."
- Two letters annotated by Clifford Odets, 1927
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12083486
  Two letters written by a young camper Milton Aion; annotated by Clifford Odets while he was a camp counselor.
- Two pen and ink sketches for Wein, 1933
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8649487
  Two pen and ink sketches for the book, Wein (published in 1933 by the Prague wine firm Jos. Oppelt's Neffe), for which Adolf Hoffmeister was the illustrator: [1]. Bottle of wine with label, "Wein," with a wine glass on either side; feather quill pen resting in glass on right hand side (22 x 30 cm. matted to 36 x 44 cm.) -- [2]. Bespeckled man reading a wine list, with "Weinkarte" printed in reverse on one of the leaves the man holds (31 x 22 cm. matted to 44 x 36 cm.).
- Hermann Hauff letters, 1855-1858
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8235594
  Six letters written to author Wilhelm Hemsen, by Hermann Hauff (in Stuttgart), dated as follows: (1) Nov. 13, 1855(?); [2] Sept. 27, 1856; [3] Nov. 6, 1856; Dec. 3, 1856; Dec. 8, 1857; and, June 19, 1858. The letters discuss Grimm's translation of an article on Shakespeare, which led to the Hauffs receiving a half dozen of Emerson's essays in translation--translations so poor Hauff could do nothing with them. But the translations of Emerson he has now received [from an unnamed translator] seem to him much better. In subsequent letters the discussion over the translation of Emerson's essays into German continues. He raises specific objections to various words and phrases, although he suggests that it's a worthy effort for a woman...He eventually decides to revise the whole of the translation. Herman Hauff became private secretary of the publisher Johann Friedrich von Cotta in 1827. Upon the death of his brother, Wilhelm Hauff, in that year, he took over as editor of the Morgenblatt für gebildete Stände, and remained in that post until his death. In addition to essays which he published in numerous journals, he was the author of Skizzen aus dem Leben und der Natur. He was active as both an editor and translator. Wilhelm Hemsen (1829-1885) was a friend of Mörike nd Nerthold Auerbach, and an acquaintance of many famous literary figures. In 1869 he became the Court Librarian in Stuttgart.
- Ludwig Tieck letter, 17 June 1839
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8264445
  Holograph letter ([4] p.), signed, from Johann Ludwig Tieck to his publisher Georg Andreas Reimer (1776-1842), dated June 17, 1839, concerning his work (in collaboration with August Wilhelm von Schlegel) on the German-language edition of Shakespeare's dramatic works, which appeared in 1838/1840 in twelve volumes.
- The apple's wedding, [19--?]
  Purchase: 2006
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/7313610
  Holograph story in verse, with handcolored illustrations.
- Mabel Decides to go to the Moon, [ca. 1950?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11667614
  A mouse named Mabel resolves to visit the moon, which she thinks is made of cheese. On her way, she meets her friend Dora the donkey, who wishes to go to the moon with her. However, their travel is delayed by the search for Dora's lost carrot seeds, and the moon wanes and disappears before they can begin their journey.